A Guide to the Governor James Monroe Executive Papers, 1799-1802
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor James Monroe Executive Papers, 1799-1802
Library of Virginia
40936
5.28 cubic feet
Governor's Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 5332-5350.
Miscellaneous Reel 5332 - Chronological Files, 1799 Dec. 7-1800 Feb. 27
Miscellaneous Reel 5333 - Chronological Files, 1800 Mar. 1-May 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5334 - Chronological Files, 1800 June 1-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5335 - Chronological Files, 1800 Sept. 1-Oct. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5336 - Chronological Files, 1800 Nov.-1801 Jan. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5337 - Chronological Files, 1801 Feb. 2-Apr. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5338 - Chronological Files, 1801 May 2-June 20
Miscellaneous Reel 5339 - Chronological Files, 1801 June 21-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5340 - Chronological Files, 1801 Sept. 6-Oct. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5341 - Chronological Files, 1801 Nov. 2-Dec. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5342 - Chronological Files, 1802 Jan. 2-Feb. 28
Miscellaneous Reel 5343 - Chronological Files, 1802 Mar. 1-Apr. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5344 - Chronological Files, 1802 May 1-June 29
Miscellaneous Reel 5345 - Chronological Files, 1802 July 1-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5346 - Chronological Files, 1802 Sept. 1-Oct. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5347 - Chronological Files, 1802 Nov.-Dec. 24 & Pardons, A-I
Miscellaneous Reel 5348 - Chronological Files, 1802 Pardons, J-P-Undated
Miscellaneous Reel 5349 - Subject Files, Gabriel's Insurrection/McCormick-Miles-Haslett Arms Contract
Miscellaneous Reel 5350 - Subject Files, McCormick-Miles-Haslett Arms Contract/Receipt for Pamphlets
Biographical Information
James Monroe was born on 28 April 1758 in Westmoreland County, Virginia, to Spence Monroe and Elizabeth Jones. A graduate of William and Mary College in 1776, Monroe enlisted as a lieutenant in the Third Virginia Regiment of the Continental Army. Monroe was promoted to major following the Battle of Trenton, and served as a colonel and aid to General William Alexander from 1777 to 1778. Monroe studied law under Governor Thomas Jefferson and was elected to the House of Delegates in 1782, however, he vacated his seat when he was appointed to the Council of State. In 1783, Monroe was chosen as a delegate to represent Virginia in the Confederation Congress which he served until 1786. He returned to the House of Delegates in 1787 and represented Spotsylvania County in the Convention of 1788 to ratify the Federal Constitution. He lost an election to James Madison in the First Congress, but was later elected to the United States Senate on 9 November 1790 to replace the deceased William Grayson. He was reelected in 1791 and served in the Senate until his resignation on 27 May 1794. President George Washington appointed Monroe Minister Plenipotentiary to France on 28 May 1794.
Monroe became Governor of Virginia on 19 December 1799. During his first one-year term in office, Monroe successfully quelled Gabriel's Insurrection, the largest slave uprising in Virginia's history until that time. Monroe's governorship too saw the completion of the Virginia Penitentiary and the Manufactory of Arms. Monroe was elected to two additional one-year terms as governor. Following his governorship, in 1803, Monroe was appointed by President Thomas Jefferson as Minister Plenipotentiary to France, and later Minister Plenipotentiary to England from 1803 until 1807. Monroe returned to the House of Delegates in 1810 and was again elected governor on 19 January 1811. Monroe's second stint as governor, however, was short-lived as he resigned following his appointment by President James Madison as Secretary of State. Simultaneously, Monroe replaced John Armstrong as Secretary of War from 1814 to 1815. The culmination of Monroe's political career occurred with his election and subsequent reelection as the fifth President of the United States from 4 March 1817 to 3 March 1825. Monroe's last significant public position took place when he was elected president of the Virginia Constitutional Convention in 1829.
Monroe married Elizabeth Kortright in 1786. They had two daughters, Elizabeth and Maria Hester. He died at the home of his youngest daughter in New York City on 4 July 1831. Originally interred at the Marble Cemetery, Monroe's remains were later reinterred twenty-five years later in Richmond's Hollywood Cemetery after appeals by Governor Henry A. Wise and the Virginia Legislature.
Scope and Content Information
James Monroe's Executive papers are organized into two series. Series have been designated for Chronological files and Subject files. The bulk of the material can be found in the Chronological files' series.
The Chronological Files series primarily consists of incoming correspondence during Monroe's three one-year terms as governor between 19 December 1799 until 24 December 1802. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments & recommendations for state positions; slave insurrections; the construction of the Virginia Penitentiary & Manufactory of Arms; the Point of Fork Arsenal; the boundary between Tennessee & Virginia; public improvements; resignations; extraditions; state expenses & revenue; quarantine of vessels; elections; Presidential electors; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; contracts; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns & certificates; qualifications; lists; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; applications; opinions; and other sundry items.
The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and Governors from other states. Federal government correspondents include Presidents John Adams & Thomas Jefferson; John Marshall & James Madison, Secretaries of State; Samuel Dexter, Secretary of War; and Virginia's delegates in Congress. President John Adams writes Governor Monroe on 25 Aug. 1800 concerning the cession of the Marine Hospital at Norfolk to the United States on condition that the government pays the balance due commissioners. Additionally, on 3 June 1802, President Thomas Jefferson writes regarding the resolution of Virginia to look for a proper place, specifically Sierra Leone, Africa, to send insurgent negroes. Jefferson also communicates on the subject of upheaval in the French West Indies (1802 Nov. 24). John Marshall, Secretary of State, forwards laws from the last session of Congress (1800 Sept. N.D.). Later, James Madison writes enclosing a complaint by the agent of the U.S. at Jamaica of certain frauds in flour shipped there (1802 Jan. 2). Samuel Dexter, Secretary of War, acknowledges receipt of a list of land warrants issued from the Virginia Land Office to the officers & soldiers who served during the Revolutionary War on Continental Establishment (1800 June 16). As senators from Virginia, Stevens Thomson Mason & Wilson Cary Nicholas write the Governor regarding an attempt to repeal the Sedition Law, the closing of the contract with Robert McCormick for the delivery of arms to Virginia, and the inspection of the arms by John Shee of Philadelphia (1800 April 29). In another letter, Mason encloses the bonds of John Shee and Robert McCormick (1800 May 15).
The majority of correspondence in James Monroe's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government. Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include John Clarke, Superintendent of Public Buildings; Martin Mims, Keeper of the Penitentiary; Archibald Blair, Clerk of the Council; Samuel Coleman, Assistant Clerk of the Council of State; Philip Norborne Nicholas, Attorney General; William Wirt, Clerk of the House of Delegates; Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate; Robert Quarles, Superintendent of the Point of Fork Arsenal; Thomas Newton, County Lieutenant & Superintendent of Quarantine for Norfolk; Samuel Shepard, Auditor of Public Accounts; and William Berkeley, Treasurer.
Two significant building projects which began by Governor James Wood continued during Monroe's governorship with work on the Penitentiary and Manufactory of Arms. John Clarke, the Superintendent of these two building projects, corresponded frequently with the Governor. Included are the following subjects respecting the Penitentiary: proposals for furnishing lime (1800 Jan. 21); proposals for painting (1800 March 15); a report on the state of the public jail for the reception of criminals sent from the district jails (1800 March 26); an advance for Charles Cox as undertaker of the painting work (1800 April 11); the kitchen (1800 April 16); an alteration in Latrobe's original plan (1800 June 7 ); problems with the militia guard posted at the Penitentiary (1800 Oct. 15); carpenter's work on the Keeper's house (1800 Dec. 20); woodwork on the interior of the cells & the removal of gunpowder from the Penitentiary (1801 March 28); an advance to John Harvie for furnishing bricks, lime, etc., for the Penitentiary & Manufactory (1801 April 26); the purchase of window glass, iron, paint, etc., for the Penitentiary & Manufactory (1801 June 20); contracts by John Harvie & Martin Mims for furnishing bricks & lime for the Penitentiary & Manufactory (1801 Oct. 18); iron apparatus for cooking (1801 Nov. 28); the status of the Penitentiary & Manufactory (1801 Dec. 4); an alteration to the Penitentiary so that it can be easily cleansed for the health of the convicts (1802 May 8); the employment of negroes confined in the Penitentiary in the yard stone-cutting (1802 May 22); the digging of the well at the Penitentiary (1802 May 24); the inscription over the entrance to the Penitentiary (1802 Aug. 7); the removal of gunpowder from the Capitol to the Penitentiary (1802 Nov. 27); and lime furnished by John Harvie (1802 Nov. 27).
John Clarke also devoted substantial correspondence to the construction, employment, and materials for the Manufactory of Arms. On 30 May 1801, Clarke writes Monroe regarding a trip north to locate artificers to work in the Manufactory. In his absence, he names William McKim as supervisor. Subsequently, on 12 June 1801, Clarke writes concerning the number of workmen to be employed in the Manufactory and the manner he proposes to conduct it after its completion. Clarke also provides details of the number of men required for various branches in the Manufactory. Similarly, in his letter dated 27 Nov. 1801, Clarke writes concerning the precise number of master armorers, clerks, commissaries, & machinists necessary for the Manufactory, along with their duties. On 23 Dec. 1801, Clarke writes the Governor defending his conduct as superintendent of the Manufactory following an inquiry by the General Assembly. On 4 Jan. 1802, Clarke encloses an estimate of the expense in the completion of the Manufactory of Arms & Penitentiary, as well as for the purchase of tools. Lastly, on 21 Aug. 1802, Clarke informs the Governor of the death of George Prosser who served as Assistant Superintendent for the Erection of Public Buildings. Additional subjects include: the digging of the foundations for the trip-hammer forge, etc., by Moses Bates (1800 March 28, April 4, & 1801 Jan. 16); work employed on the machinery (1800 April 5); the roofs of the Manufactory buildings (1800 April 18); contracts for shingles (1800 April 18 & May 9); the contract of George Williamson to clean & stamp state arms (1800 May 23, 30, & 7 June); masonry work by Niman Wise & James Carney (1800 April 6, June 27, Sept. 23, Oct. 5, & 1801 Nov. 13); the distribution of public arms to the militia of the several counties (1800 July 23, Aug. 10, & Sept. 25); examination of arms sent by James Swan for the militia (1800 Oct. 2); additional bricks (1800 Oct. 6); proposal by George Williamson to repair old arms at the Penitentiary (1800 Oct. 7); the contracts of Jesse Payne to furnish timber and John Harvie for bricks & lime (1800 Nov. 1 & 14); arms sent to the Penitentiary (1801 Jan. 7); the rental of a house for the accommodation of machinery of the Manufactory (1801 Jan. 20); the removal of arms from the Point of Fork Arsenal to Richmond (1801 Feb. 4); the preparation of the garret of the Capitol to receive arms from Point of Fork (1801 Feb. 14); barracks for the Armory Guard at the former hemp inspection warehouse near Rocketts (1801 Feb. 15 & 17); the appointment of a superintendent & his salary (1801 April 17); the employment of artificers at the Point of Fork Arsenal to repair arms until the Manufactory is ready (1801 May 9); contracts for artificers (1801 July 6); artificers & materials for the Manufactory at Philadelphia (1801 July 23); gunsmiths in New York & the examination of the state prison there (1801 July 27); proposals for the manufacture of arms (1801 Oct. 13); the employment of artificers (1801 Sept. 25 & Nov. 13); the procurement of armorers from Springfield, Massachusetts (1801 Oct. 31); neglected pieces of ordnance throughout the state (1801 Dec. 23); rations for soldiers (1802 Jan. 9 & 30); cut stone for the steeple (1802 Jan. 18); bells for the Manufactory, Penitentiary, & Capitol Building (1801 April 27, May 2, & 1802 Feb. 25); timber for fixing up the apparatus (1802 Feb. 13 & 24); an invoice of items furnished by John Hodson of Birmingham, England (1802 Feb. 25); the examination of arms sent by George Wheeler (1802 March 11); musket stocks & the employment of gunsmiths to clean the arms stored in the Capitol (1802 March 12 & 27); Henry Foxall's improvements for casting ordnance (1802 March 12 & May 22); apprentices to work in the Manufactory (1802 April 10); the account of Jesse Payne for timber (1802 May 12); the receipt of gun flints (1802 May 22); the examination of the public arms in the roof of the Capitol by Barlow & Hayes (1802 June 5); the foundation for the boring mill for ordnance (1802 July 24); the purchase of walnut timber for gun stocks from the United States (1802 July 23 & 24); reimbursement to artificers for travel expenses (1802 Aug. 7); the walls of the Foundry House & Armory (1802 Oct. 2); and the kitchens of the Manufactory (1802 Nov. 7).
John Clarke was also involved in miscellaneous projects including a project to construct a new tobacco warehouse along the James River Canal in Richmond. On 28 March 1801, Clarke enclosed proposals to the Governor for the tobacco warehouse. Shortly thereafter, he submitted proposals for building the walls (1801 June 13). On 24 July 1802, Clarke writes the Governor concerning the posts for the warehouse. He also writes regarding the purchase of slate from either New York or Philadelphia (1802 Sept. 18 & Nov. 8).
Martin Mims, Keeper of the Penitentiary, communicates with Governor Monroe regarding numerous subjects related to prisoners and the Penitentiary. Included in these papers is Mims' bond as Keeper of the Penitentiary (1800 March 25), along with a memorandum of negroes sentenced for transportation & sent to the Penitentiary for safekeeping (1802 Oct. 17). Among his correspondence are the following topics: extra brick work done in the Penitentiary in 1799 (1800 Jan. 4); the employment of George Anderson Stile to instruct the prisoners in making nails at the Penitentiary (1800 July 12); the employment of additional guards at the Penitentiary (1800 Sept. 6); rations for prisoners an escape attempt (1802 Jan. 13); a statement of the distribution of public arms to the militia (1802 May 4); an escape attempt by five prisoners (1802 July 24); the number of criminals who have been sent to the Penitentiary from each term since Fall 1800 (1802 Nov. 18); and a report of the Board of Inspectors of the Penitentiary re. the his conduct (1802 July 12).
Archibald Blair & Samuel Coleman, as Clerk & Assistant Clerk of the Council, communicate with the Governor regularly through the Council Office. Blair encloses proceedings of the Council regarding topics such as the appointment of John Cowper as Vice Consul of Sweden (1800 March 15) and the calling out a proportion of the militia of Henrico, Chesterfield, & Richmond (1800 Sept. 6). Also, Blair writes on 7 June 1800 regarding a motion to remove him as Clerk of the Council during his absence. Samuel Coleman, as Assistant Clerk to the Council, both sent and received letters from Governor Monroe. Monroe informed the Council on several occasions of his temporary absence from office (1800 March 5, 1800 May 11, & 1800 Sept. 26). On 21 Feb. 1801, Monroe encloses a letter from Philip Sheppard requesting $500 for Pharaoh, one of his slaves who discovered the intended insurrection. Monroe also discusses an act to purchase the freedom of Pharaoh & Tom as a reward for their service. Coleman's letter in response also relates to these slaves who assisted in the prevention of the insurrection (1801 Feb. 28).
Attorney General Robert Brooke died in office on 27 February 1800. Edmund Randolph assisted the Governor with opinions during Brooke's absence with illness and until a replacement was appointed. On 8 January 1800, Governor Monroe requests Randolph's opinion on the legality of trying slaves brought from Maryland into Southampton where they murdered their masters. Randolph's letter in reply on the same date indicates that these slaves were properly tried since they were not in the Commonwealth for the 12-month period required by the law of December 1792. Randolph also served as counsel for the Commonwealth in its negotiations with Robert Pollard concerning payment for arms furnished by him (1800 Feb. 8). Lastly, Randolph informs the Governor of the suit in the Federal Court of Hamilton vs. Newton in favor of the defendant (1800 June 5). Philip Norborne Nicholas was appointed Attorney General on 15 March 1800. In a letter dated 6 June 1800, Nicholas encloses a letter from David Robertson, County Attorney for the District of Brunswick, regarding a fine imposed on Washington Crofts. Nicholas provides his opinion on several subjects including: the case of Thomas Carter, a revenue collector for the United States, who wished to serve as a militia officer in Virginia (1800 Aug. 3); the right of the Executive to condemn lands for the use of sick in cases of quarantine (1800 Sept. 6); the admission of negroes into Virginia who were taken as a prize to a U.S. vessel of war (1801 Feb. 11); the emancipation of the slaves Pharaoh & Tom (1801 March 10); his prosecution in the case against Dr. J.K. Read (1801 April 30 & 1801 May 20); the transportation of seamen under contract to perform a voyage (1801 May 20); the suit of De Beaumarchais (1801 Dec. 11 & 24, 1802 Feb. 20); public lands in Buckingham County purchased for supporting a blast furnace by Balentine & Reveley (1802 Feb. 20); deputies or assistants for Martin Mims as Keeper of the Penitentiary (1802 May 23); and the Little River Turnpike Company (1802 Dec. 6).
William Wirt, Clerk of the House of Delegates, and Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate, often submit legislation and qualifications of election to the Governor. Wirt submits a resolution requesting a statement of arms which have been issued from the public arsenal to the militia (1799 Dec. 20). Also included are notices for the following elections: John Clopton & James Wood to the Privy Council (1799 Dec. 11); Samuel McCraw & John Mayo to the Privy Council (1799 Dec. 11); Alexander Stewart to the Privy Council in place of Hardin Burnley (1799 Dec. 12); William Foushee to the Privy Council in place of John Allen (1799 Dec. 12); James Monroe as Governor (1799 Dec. 19); William Berkeley as Treasurer (1799 Dec. 21 & 1802 Jan. 5); Archibald Stuart as Judge of the General Court in place of James Henry (1800 Jan. 13); James Wood as Privy Councilor (1800 May 29); David Coleman, John Shore, David Carroll Brent, & John Bowyer as electors for the Presidential & Vice Presidential election (1800 Dec. 2); Meriwether Jones as Public Printer (1800 Dec. 4 & 1801 Dec. 9); Philip Norborne Nicholas as Attorney General in place of Robert Brooke (1800 Dec. 4); James Monroe as Governor (1801 Dec. 10); Samuel Tyler & John Clopton to the Privy Council (1801 Dec. 12); John Brown as Judge of the District Court of Chancery at Staunton (1802 Jan. 27); and William Wirt as Judge of the District Court of Chancery at Williamsburg (1802 Jan. 28).
Maj. Robert Quarles submits quarterly returns of arms, ordnance, & public stores at Point of Fork (1800 Jan. 1, 1800 April 1, 1800 July 1, & 1800 Oct. 1). In addition, Quarles writes concerning powder to be sent to Richmond (1800 Jan. 4); an advance for contingent expenses (1800 April 2); rations for the additional guard (1800 Sept. 3); enlistments, an advance for clothing, & a contract for rations (1800 Sept. 27); contractor's bond for rations during the ensuing year (1800 Oct. 18); public property at the Point of Fork (1801 March 6); the completion of the removal of arms from the Point of Fork to Richmond (1801 April 12).contracts for rent of public lands & houses at Point of Fork (1801 July 4); payment to John Gray for boxing up lumber from the Arsenal to Richmond (1802 Aug. 14); and renting out public lands at the Arsenal (1802 Sept. 27).
Thomas Newton, Jr., County Lieutenant & Superintendent of Quarantine for Norfolk Borough, frequently writes the Governor concerning infectious diseases & the quarantine of vessels (1800 July 12, 13, & 30, 1800 Aug. 22 & 29, 1800 Sept. 6, 1800 Oct. 9, 1801 Sept. 30, & 1802 Aug. 13). Newton's letter on 8 May 1800 relates to the valuation of the Gosport lands in Norfolk. In his letter dated 1800 Aug. 22, Newton mentions his commission for holding the election of electors for President & Vice President. On 2 Sept. 1800, he provides a list of persons who died from disease since his last return. In addition, Newton sometimes encloses reports of vessels visited & examined by Dr. J.K. Read (1802 Sept. 17, 1802 Oct. 18 & 26). Newton also writes regarding a prize vessel belonging to one of the New England governments with a cargo of thirty slaves bound for Havana from Guinea which was captured by Capt. Baron of the frigate Chesapeake. Several letters by Newton relate to the quarantine of a Spanish vessel called the Brig Ann (1801 May 16, 17, & 27). Newton was also involved in the Dismal Swamp Company and reports on its progress (1801 Oct. 28, 1801 Nov. 14 & 20, 1802 Sept. 27).